Guide to the Danbury Ledgers 1826-1932 (Bulk 1900-1918) DRG 1&2 DRG 1&2
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Danbury Ledgers
1826-1932, (Bulk 1900-1918)
1900-1918
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
City of Danbury, Conn.
DRG 1&2
24 Linear Feet, 24 Reels, 300 bound ledgers
This collection includes various Danbury municipal records including military service lists, voting lists, real estate transactions, public utilities expenditures mainly from the early 20th century.
24 Reels
Provenance
This collection was obtained by WCSU history faculty out of discarded City of Danbury records. The original material was damaged in a flood and has been microfilmed. Most of the items are available at the City Clerks Office.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. Researchers must use microfilm.
Historical/Biographical Note
The City of Danbury maintains records on taxes, expenditures and property. Presumably as some of these ledgers were deemed to fragile to handle they were duplicated for use in the Clerks office. Some of them may have passed their retention schedule.
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes: Voter Lists, Grand lists, Personal Tax Enrollment, Grantors Index, Danbury-Orders to be Paid, Receipts and Disbursements, Treasurer, Municipal Service Expenditures, Danbury - Military Records - Enrollments/ Recapitulation, Water Applications, Danbury Street Sprinkling, Danbury Water Commissioner Accounts and Records, Danbury - Utilities, Sewer and Paving Assessments, Sewage Plant, Daily Log, Sewer Connection Permits, and the Census of the School District from 1900.
In 1975 two Western Connecticut State University professors, Truman Warner and Herbert Janick, acquired a significant collection of Danbury records (a mixture of town (borough) and city records). An official transfer of custody for these documents does not exist, but it is known that, at the time, the City of Danbury had earmarked the records for disposal. Through the years, it also appears that some records may have been lost, stolen, or discarded. A detailed documentation does not exist.
These Danbury ledgers were sent to Northeast Document Conservation Center for preservation microfilming in 2007. Some items were discovered after the materials were microfilmed; they are included in this inventory noted as "ledgers" and are available in hard copy.
Arrangement
Information is generally in chronological order in each resource.
The files are grouped into 1 series.
Danbury (Conn.) -- Economic conditions -- Statistics.; Danbury (Conn.) -- Social conditions.; Voters' lists.; Municipal government records.; Danbury (Conn.); Lists (document genres); Ledgers (account books).; Danbury (Conn.) -- History.
- Elections - Voter Lists, 1882-1927; ledger: 5-480; Microfilm Reel: 1-14
  Scope and Contents
  Bound volumes of voters for districts of the Borough (up to 1889) and City (1889 and later) of Danbury, CT. Elections were under the jurisdiction of the Town of Danbury and not the City until consolidation. Books give names and addresses of all registered voters for each election. Check marks indicate which person actually voted in each election. Party affiliations are not recorded. Voters are listed by district for state elections and by ward for town elections. Covers on ledgers state "# district" or "# ward" or "to be made." Included are bound volumes of women voters for pre-1920 elections and the 1920 (ledger 209-213) election where women were first permitted to vote in general elections. Ledgers for primary enrollment indicate party affiliations as do some from the later 1920s (ledgers: 218, 220, 222-228).
  General
  DG 101
  - Voter list, ledger #5-480, and un-numbered, 1882-1928 (Item 1-230)
- Accounting
  - Town of Danbury - Orders to be Paid, 1885-1899 (Item ledger: 1-5)
    General note
    Microfilm Reel: 19-20
    DF160
  - Town of Danbury - Treasurer, Receipts and Disbursements, 1894-1902 (Item ledgers 6-7)
    Microfilm Reel: 20-21
    DF163
  - Borough of Danbury - Municipal Service Expenditures, 1880-1883 (Item ledger 8)
    Microfilm Reel: 21
    DF171
- Grand Lists (taxes), 1826-1902; ledger: 1-63; Microfilm Reel: 15-17
  Scope and Contents note
  Bound volumes of tax lists for the Town of Danbury. Ledgers are divided into residents, non-residents, and minorities. Some years list value of public buildings such as churches, schools, courthouse, and jail. Tax lists for individual schools are also listed for some years.
  DG103
  - Grand List ledger: 1, 1826 (Item Grand List ledger: 1)
  - Grand List ledger: 2, 1827 (Item Grand List ledger: 2)
  - Grand List ledger: 03a, 1828 (Item Grand List ledger: 03a)
  - Grand List ledger: 03b, 18xx (Item Grand List ledger: 03b)
  - Grand List ledger: 03c, 1849 (Item Grand List ledger: 03c)
  - Grand List ledger: 04a, 1851 (Item Grand List ledger: 04a)
  - Grand List ledger: 04b, 1853 (Item Grand List ledger: 04b)
  - Grand List ledger: 05a, 1856 (Item Grand List ledger: 05a)
  - Grand List ledger: 05b, 1856 (Item Grand List ledger: 05b)
  - Grand List ledger: 6, 1857 (Item Grand List ledger: 6)
  - Grand List ledger: 08b, 1863? (Item Grand List ledger: 08b)
  - Grand List ledger: 9, 1863 (Item Grand List ledger: 9)
  - Grand List ledger: 18, 1873 (Item Grand List ledger: 18)
  - Grand List ledger: 19, 1874 (Item Grand List ledger: 19)
  - Grand List ledger: 20, 1875 (Item Grand List ledger: 20)
  - Grand List ledger: 21, 1876 (Item Grand List ledger: 22)
  - Grand List ledger: 22, 1877 (Item Grand List ledger: 22)
  - Grand List ledger: 23, 1878 (Item Grand List ledger: 23)
  - Grand List ledger: 24, 1879 (Item Grand List ledger: 24)
  - Grand List ledger: 25, 1880 (Item Grand List ledger: 25)
  - Grand List ledger: 26, 1881 (Item Grand List ledger: 26)
  - Grand List ledger: 29, 1882 (Item Grand List ledger: 29)
  - Grand List ledger: 30, 1883 (Item Grand List ledger: 30)
  - Grand List ledger: 31, 1885 (Item Grand List ledger: 31)
  - Grand List ledger: 32, 1886 (Item Grand List ledger: 32)
  - Grand List ledger: 33, 1887 (Item Grand List ledger: 33)
  - Grand List ledger: 34, 1888 (Item Grand List ledger: 34)
  - Grand List ledger: 35, 1888? (Item Grand List ledger: 35)
  - Grand List ledger: 36, 1889 (Item Grand List ledger: 36)
  - Grand List ledger: 62, 1902 (Item Grand List ledger: 62)
  - Grand List (Center School District) ledger: 63, 1903 (Item Grand List ledger: 63)
- Taxation
  - Danbury-Taxes - Street Lists, 1899-1909 (Item ledgers 261-269)
    Microfilm Reel: 18
    DG112.1-112.9; DG112.6 is missing; DG112.9 is not digitized
  - Danbury - Personal Tax Enrollment, 1915 (Item ledger 270)
    DG115
    Alphabetical list of men, ages 21-60, owing taxes. Includes notation of exemptions (i.e., military service, police officer). 1 ledger.
  - [DG120] Liens - Centre School District, 1903-1903 (Item ledger 271)
    Not microfilmed. Alphabetical listing of tax liens in connection with the payment of school taxes. Includes amt of tax, amt of lien, when lien was affixed and paid. 1 ledger.
  - [DG121 20] Danbury Land Records, ca.1910s-ca.1910s (Item ledger 272)
    Not microfilmed. Index re purchase and sale of property. Lists property purchased, location, date, mortgage, lease information, etc. Spine reads "Grantees 121-130, General Index #20." Inside "Index to Land Records Danbury, Conn."
  - Danbury - Grantors Index, 1906-1912 (Item ledger 273)
    DG121_122
  - Board of Estimates and Taxation, 1911-1919 (Item ledger 274)
    DG130
  - [DG165] Board of Relief, City of Danbury, 1898-1900 (Item ledgers 275-278)
    Not microfilmed. Includes names, amt of relief issued and description of the person(s) situation. 4 ledgers.
  - [DG165] Board of Relief, City of Danbury, 1898-1900 (Box 1)
    Not microfilmed. 1 Leather bound ledger from 1898-1900 tracking relief payments. Includes index of names with a list of expenditures. Many of the expenditures are for coal. Very brittle.
- Military
  Pensioners and pool of draftees and deferments
  - Danbury - Military Records - Enrollments/ Recapitulation, 1865-1912 (Item ledgers 279-291)
    Microfilm Reel: 22
    DM140
- Utilities
  - Water Applications, 1880-1914 (Item ledgers 280-285)
    DU122
  - Danbury Street Sprinkling, 1908-1919 (Item ledgers 286-287)
    Microfilm Reel: 23
    DU123
  - Danbury Water Commissioner Accounts and Records, 1860-1885 (Item ledger 289)
    DU124
  - Danbury - Utilities, 1894-1895 (Item ledger 290)
    DU125
  - Sewer and Paving Assessments, 1888-1894 (Item ledgers 291-292)
    DU127
  - Sewage Plant, Daily Log, 1888-1895 (Item ledgers 293-294)
    DU128
  - Sewer Connection Permits, 1910-1914 (Item ledger 288)
    DU129
- Schools
  - Census of the School District, 1900 (Item ledger 299)
    Microfilm Reel: 24
    Schools
  - [DSch172] School Board Committee, 1904-1910 (Item Ledgers 295-296)
    Not microfilmed. Appropriations and expenditures. 2 ledgers.
  - [DSch174] Minutes of School Board Meetings, 1892-1911 (Item Ledgers 297-298)
    Not microfilmed. School Board was called Board of School Visitors. 2 Ledgers.